Doctor Who (1963) 04x09  The Evil of the Daleks (Episode 3)
《神秘博士》老版第四季第九集 《Daleks 的邪恶》 (第三部分)
【翻译】巴蛮子sz
【时间轴】巴蛮子sz
【校对】巴蛮子sz
基于 opentitles.org 英文字幕翻译
Sincro: wyxchari
DALEK 1: The humans have been told to begin the test.
已经通知人类开始实验
DALKE 2: Any delay will result in death.
任何人拖延都将处死
DALEK 2: There will be no delay!
不允许有拖延!
MAXTIBLE: Mollie, Mollie. Mr. McCrimmon has been kidnapped!
Mollie, Mollie. McCrimmon先生被绑架了！
MAXTIBLE: It means the end of us unless we can find him quickly.
这意味着我们都将完蛋了, 除非赶紧找到他
(The Doctor shows them some straw he has found, then walks off.)
(博士把他发现的一些稻草拿给他们看, 然后走开了)
DOCTOR: Straw.
稻草
WATERFIELD: I beg your pardon?
你说什么？
DOCTOR: A piece of straw.
一小截稻草
TOBY: Had a cosy little sleep, young swell?
小觉睡的还舒服吧, 年轻人？
TOBY: Lively, is it? Maybe you'd like to sleep again?
醒了吧, 对不？是不是还想睡一觉？
TOBY: I've got Mr. Nod here. He'll have you snorin' as good as ever.
我这里有位“点头”先生, 他会让你的呼噜震天响的
JAMIE: What do you want?
你想要怎么样？
TOBY: I'm to be well paid. Have no fear of that.
我会得到很好的报酬, 我不怕那个。
JAMIE: Oh, and for what? I don't know you.
哦, 得到什么报酬？ 我不认识你
TOBY: This your man, sir?
这是你要的人吧, 先生？
TERRALL: Toby! What in Hades have you done?
Toby! 你到底干了什么？
TOBY: Why, I, uh... brought 'im from the house, like you said.
为什么。。。我把他从房子里带过来了啊, 你这么说的
TERRALL: I said nothing of the kind.
我可没说这样的话
TOBY: Well ya did, sir! Honest ya did.
A guinea ya promised me.
你说过, 先生！你真的说过。许诺给我一基尼呢
TOBY: I... I done what ya said. You don't get outta payin'.
我。。我已经做了你要求的, 你别想不给钱
TERRALL: Be careful how you speak to me, Toby!
注意你跟我说话的方式, Toby!
TERRALL: There's your money. Get out!
这是给你的钱, 出去！
(Toby picks up the coin Terrall threw, then leaves.)
(Toby 捡起 Terrall 扔下的硬币, 离开了)
TERRALL: Where's Toby?
Toby 哪儿去了？
JAMIE: You just sent him about his business.
Look, what's the matter? Are you all right?
你刚把他打发走了啊。这到底怎么回事？你还好吗？
TERRALL: Where's Victoria Waterfield?
Victoria Waterfield 在哪儿？
JAMIE: I don't know.
我不知道
TERRALL: Yes, you do.
知道
JAMIE: I tell you, I don't even know her!
我告诉你, 我都不认识她
TERRALL: You're in the house, a friend of Maxtible's. You must know!
你在这个房子里, 你是 Maxtible 的朋友, 你肯定知道！
JAMIE: No, listen, I'm te...
不, 听我说, 我说的是。。。
(A metal attachment can be see on Terrall's neck.)
(Terrall 的脖子上可以见到金属物件在反光)
TERRALL: Ha, I must apologize for that villain Toby.
哈, 我必须为那个恶棍 Toby 的事向你道歉。
TERRALL: He was telling lies, of course. I shall escort you to the house.
当然, 他说的都是谎言。我护送你回房子里去
JAMIE: Uh, You... you... you just asked me about Victoria Waterfield.
哦, 你。。。你。。你刚才还在问我 Victoria Waterfield 的事情
TERRALL: Now, she's in Paris. I'm afraid I haven't introduced myself - Arthur Terrall.
现在, 她还在巴黎呢。恐怕我还没有介绍我自己 - Arthur Terrall
JAMIE: Well, never mind about that. Did you or did you not
ask that man to knock me on the head and bring me in here?
哦, 先别管那个了。你有还是没有, 叫那个人把我打晕再把我带过来？
TERRALL: I, oh...certainly not!
我, 噢。。。当然没有
JAMIE: Doctor
博士
TERRALL: Oh. I see you're in good hands now.
I won't detain you any further.
哦, 我看你现在碰到朋友了。我就不再耽误你了。
TERRALL: Good day, Doctor.
日安, 博士
DOCTOR: Oh, good day to you.
哦, 你也日安
JAMIE: He's mad. Stark, staring mad!
他疯了, 他完全疯了
TERRALL: Yes, I know. I was listening. Let's have a look at
that head of yours. Come along.
是的, 我知道, 刚才我听到了。我们来看看你的头吧, 过来
JAMIE: Look, it's all right, Doctor. One minute he says this,
the next minute he says that. Can you make it out, Doctor?
哦, 问题不大, 博士。前一分钟他在说这个, 后一分钟他又说那个。你搞明白了吗？
JAMIE: I'm knocked on the head and I'm brought in here.
Then that man Terrall enters and denies having ordered the other man to do it.
我被人敲晕了脑袋, 带到了这里。那个Terrall 进来之后否认是他让那个人干的。
JAMIE: Well, then he changes, and starts asking about Victoria Waterfield
and in the next breath, he tells me she's in Paris!
然后, 他又变了, 开始问 Victoria Waterfield 的事情, 下一秒钟他又告诉我她在巴黎！
DOCTOR: I know what's happened to Victoria.
我知道 Victoria 发生了什么事
JAMIE: What has?
什么事？
DOCTOR: She's a prisoner of the Daleks.
她成了 Daleks 的囚徒
DALEK: Hurry!
快点！
VICTORIA: Why am I being moved?
Are you taking me back to my father?
为什么要转移我？你们要带我回到我父亲那里吗？
DALEK: No, you are being moved. Pick up your cover. Follow.
不, 只是给你换个地方。带上你的外套。跟上。
(She picks up a bundle of clothes from the bed and stands up.)
(她从床上拿起一叠衣服, 站了起来)
DALEK: Do not be afraid. You are not to be exterminated.
不用害怕, 你不会被终结掉
(She follows the Dalek down the corridor.)
(她跟在 Dalek 后面沿着走廊前行)
(A second Dalek arrives.)
(有一个 Dalek 过来了)
DALEK: Do not delay.
不要磨蹭
(She walks down the corridor between the Daleks.)
(她从两个 Dalek 之间走过, 沿着走廊往前走)
(Victoria stops to look out of a window.)
(Victoria 停下来, 往窗外望去)
DALEK: Move.
走
(Jamie enters the room unobserved and listens from behind a screen.)
(Jamie 前无声息地进了房间, 在一个屏风后面躲着)
WATERFIELD: You've warned him - told him about the Daleks?
你警告他了, 把 Daleks 的事情告诉他了？
DOCTOR: Yes, of course I did!
是的, 我当然会这样
WATERFIELD: But you were expressly told...
但你被命令禁止。。。
DOCTOR: Oh, fiddlesticks!
哦, 别胡说！
DOCTOR: Bosh! Jamie will cooperate. You may be certain of that.
胡说！ Jamie 会合作的。这个事情你可以放心
WATERFIELD: Are you sure?
你确定吗？
DOCTOR: Yes, perfectly sure. Jamie will do everything he is asked to do.
Now come along, we must go and find Maxtible.
是的, 完全确定。你让 Jamie 做任何事情, 他都会去做。来吧, 我们去找 Maxtible
DALEK: The female human being has been moved.
那个人类女性已经被转移
MAXTIBLE: Everything is prepared.
一切已经准备就绪
DALEK: The testing equipment is ready?
实验设备准备好了吗？
MAXTIBLE: I think you will be pleased with the man,
I've had specially brought from London. Ah, he works in my house.
我像你会对这个人满意的, 我特意把他从伦敦带过来, 他在那边一直帮我做事
DALEK: Show me!
带来见我
MAXTIBLE: You will understand that he is rather simple.
你要明白他是一个相当简单的人
MAXTIBLE: He's quite dumb, but, uh... that has its advantages for us.
他很笨, 不过。。。对我们而言这是个优势
MAXTIBLE: His mind is, how shall I say, undeveloped.
他的大脑, 怎么说呢, 不太发达
MAXTIBLE: He will not understand you, the Daleks.
Uh, I mean he will be terrified of you.
他搞不懂你们 Daleks。我是说, 他会害怕你们
DALEK: Show me.
带来见我
MAXTIBLE: Ohh, I beg your pardon, uh...
哦, 我很抱歉
(The Dalek enters the cabinet and closes the door.)
(Dalek 进了柜子, 关上了门)
MAXTIBLE: Kemel!
MAXTIBLE: Will you come with me?
你跟我来
MAXTIBLE: I want you to stand here.
No, no, no, no, no, face the cabinet. Good.
我要你站在这里, 不, 不, 不, 面朝柜子。好了
MAXTIBLE: Now, bend that.
现在, 掰弯那个
(Kemel strips off his waistcoat and shirt.)
(Kemel 脱下坎肩和衬衣)
(Maxtible takes the bent bar and looks towards the cabinet.)
(Maxtible 拿过掰弯的铁棍, 往柜子方向望去)
MAXTIBLE: Excellent Kemel, excellent.
Now, you'll help me with these stools.
很好, Kemel, 很好。现在, 帮我弄一下这几个凳子
(Maxtible picks up a wooden plank and lays it across the stools.)
(Maxtible 拿过来一个厚木棍, 架在两个条凳之间)
MAXTIBLE: Now, Kemel. One blow. Break the plank!
现在, Kemel, 一次把这跟木头打断!
MAXTIBLE: Very good Kemel. I'm very pleased with you.
Now you can put on your jacket. Come over here.
很好, Kemel, 我对你很满意。现在你可以穿上你的夹克了。到这里来
(Maxtible puts the stools away.)
(Maxtible 把条凳挪开了)
MAXTIBLE: Now, I want you to listen carefully. See this man?
到这里来。现在, 我想要你听仔细了, 看到这个人了吗？
MAXTIBLE: Now, I'm going to take you to a place that I want you to guard,
现在, 我要带你去一个地方, 期望你做好守卫工作
MAXTIBLE: and this young man will try and get past you
and you are not to let him. Do you understand?
而这个年轻人会试图越过你, 你不能允许他这样做, 你明白吗？
MAXTIBLE: Oh, he's an evil villain, Kemel, a cutthroat
who would gladly murder us all in our beds, if he could.
哦, 他是一个邪恶的恶棍, Kemel,
他会残忍地将我们所有人杀死在床上的, 如果他有机会的话
MAXTIBLE: You will remember this man, hmm?
你要记住这个人, 嗯？
MAXTIBLE: Right. Well, you come with me and I will direct you.
好了, 你跟我来, 我带你去
(They both leave.)
(他俩都离开了)
(The Dalek comes out of the cabinet and looks at the bent iron bar.)
(Dalek 从柜子里面出来, 观察那根掰弯的铁棍)
(Maxtible moves over to a candle and lights it.)
(Maxtible 走去拿了一根蜡烛, 把它点亮)
MAXTIBLE: You wait here. This is the entrance to the south wing of my house,
你在这里等着, 这里是我房子的南厢入口
MAXTIBLE: and through here will pass the man I showed you in the picture.
图片里面那个人就会从这里过来,
MAXTIBLE: The door itself is an obstacle.
这门就是一个屏障
(Maxtible presses the wall and it opens.)
(Maxtible 在墙上按了一下, 墙打开了)
MAXTIBLE: No, no, wait!
不, 不, 等等！
(Sharp metal spike lunge out across the entrance.)
(锋利的金属尖刺突然窜了出来, 封住了入口)
(He presses a different part of the wall
and spikes slowly retract into the wall.)
(他在墙上另外一个位置按了一下, 尖刺慢慢缩了回去)
MAXTIBLE: Now, if he gets through here, you will deal with him. Go now.
现在, 如果他到这里来, 你要对付他。去吧
(Kemel goes through the alcove.)
(Kemel 穿过暗室)
(Maxtible closes the alcove, blows out the candle and leaves.)
(Maxtible 关闭了暗室的门, 吹灭蜡烛, 离开了)
DALEK: We do not trust you.
我们不信任你
DOCTOR: Then we're quits, aren't we?
那我们退出, 可以吗？
DALEK: But we have your time machine.
但你的时间机器在我们手上
DOCTOR: Yes.
是的
DALEK: So, you will obey us.
所以, 你要服从我们
DOCTOR: They want the "Human Factor", is that right?
他们想要“人类特质”, 对吗？
Yes, that is what they want.
是的, 这就是他们想要的
DOCTOR: Very complex. And you want to introduce
this "human factor" into the race of Daleks?
这很复杂。你们期望把“人类特质”加入到 Daleks 种族中去？
DALEK: Yes, the conquest of humanity has eluded us.
The Daleks must know why.
是的, 人类的征服能力让我们很困惑。Daleks 必须明白为什么
DOCTOR: But, why choose Jamie for this test?
但是, 为什么挑选 Jamie 做实验？
DALEK: His travelling with you makes him unique.
他跟你一起旅行, 这让他变得独特
DOCTOR: But why him? Why not me?
但为什么是他, 为什么不是我？
DALEK: Request denied.
拒绝回答
DOCTOR: Why?
为什么？
DALEK: You have travelled too much through time.
You are more than human.
你在时间中旅行得太久了, 你不仅仅是个人类了
DOCTOR: I see.
我明白了
DOCTOR: What is this?
这是什么？
MAXTIBLE: They have been brought from the Dalek planet.
他们是从 Dalek 星球带过来的
DOCTOR: Skaro!
(注: Daleks 的母星)
DALEK: Yes, their life force is dormant.
Before it is activated, we want...
是的。他们目前处于休眠状态, 激活之后, 我们想要。。。
DOCTOR: You want the "human factor" introduced. I see.
你们想要引入“人类特质”, 我知道了
DALEK: You will obey us!
你要服从我们！
DOCTOR: I will make up my own mind!
我会自己拿主意！
MAXTIBLE: Do not antagonize them, Doctor.
They will destroy your time machine!
不要激怒他们, 博士。他们会毁了你的时间机器的！
MAXTIBLE: And if I agree, it means the creation of a race of super-Daleks!
但如果我同意, 那就意味着超级 Daleks 的诞生！
DOCTOR: My TARDIS... I have no choice, do I?
Very well. I agree.
我的 TARDIS。。。我没有选择, 有吗？好吧, 我同意了
DALEK: The human being with you must not be aware of the trial.
跟着你的那个人必须对这项实验不知情
DOCTOR: I quite understand.
我很明白
DALEK: Make him begin the test!
让他开始实验！
(The Dalek moves into the cabinet.)
(Dalek 回到了柜子里)
DOCTOR: What must Jamie do?
Jamie 必须干什么？
DOCTOR: Attempt to rescue Waterfield's daughter.
尝试营救 Waterfield 的女儿
MOLLIE: There we are, sir.
TERRALL: Thank you, Mollie.
谢谢你, Mollie
RUTH: Arthur, I'd like you to meet Mr. McCrimmon.
Arthur, 我引你见一下 McCrimmon 先生
TERRALL: May I ask what you are doing in this house?
我能问问你在这个房子里面干什么吗？
JAMIE: I was just about to ask you the same thing.
我也正要问你同一个问题
RUTH: Oh, you gentlemen have been introduced?
哦, 有人已经介绍两位先生认识了？
JAMIE: Aye, we've met.
是, 我们碰过面
TERRALL: It seems, Ruth, your father has the oddest collection of house guests these days.
看起来, Ruth 小姐, 你父亲这几天招待了一大堆奇怪的客人啊
RUTH: Now Arthur, please!
Arthur, 别这样
RUTH: You must forgive him, Mr. McCrimmon.
你得原谅他, McCrimmon 先生
JAMIE: Ah, it's becoming a habit.
啊, 都已经习惯了
TERRALL: I don't care for insolence.
我并不太在意这些无礼的行为
JAMIE: Well, I'm not keen on arrogance myself!
哈, 我也不太在乎那些自大的家伙
RUTH: Why, you bite at each other as if you were old enemies!
为什么, 你们俩就好像宿敌一样要互相咬？
JAMIE: I'm sorry if I seem rude.
如果我看起来比较粗鲁, 我很抱歉
RUTH: Come, I want you to be friends.
Won't you be so, to please me?
好了, 我期望你们成为朋友。你们可以吗, 就给我点面子？
RUTH: Arthur... Arthur, what is it?
Excuse me. Arthur! What's the matter?
Arthur... Arthur, 怎么了？ 对不起。Arthur！什么情况？
(Terrall and Ruth leave.)
(Terrall 和 Ruth 离开了)
MOLLIE: Sir?
先生？
JAMIE: Yes?! Oh, I wish you'd call me Jamie.
什么事？ 哦, 我期望你叫我 Jamie
MOLLIE: Oh, I couldn't do that sir. What would the master say?
噢, 我不能那样做, 先生。不知道主人会怎么说我呢
JAMIE: Oh, who cares! Ah, What can I do for you?
哦, 谁在乎！啊, 有什么能帮到你的？
MOLLIE: If you'd tell me where your bags are, sir -
yours and the Doctor's - I'll have them taken up to your room.
如果你能告诉我你的包裹在哪儿 —— 你和博士的 —— 我会让人把他们带到你的房间来的
JAMIE: Aye. well, Mollie...
啊, 这个, Mollie...
MOLLIE: Listen to me, "have them taken. "
I dare say I'll be doin' it meself!
听我说, 我说“让人带过来”, 其实我会亲自做的！
JAMIE: You see, we didn't have time to pick up the luggage.
It'll be following.
你看, 我们并没有时间收拾行李, 过两天才会送来
MOLLIE: Oh.
哦
JAMIE: Why do you say that you'll be doing it yourself?
为什么你说你要自己做？
MOLLIE: Well, they do say, sir, that the house is haunted.
哦, 他们说, 先生, 这房子闹鬼
MOLLIE: Mr. Kitson, the butler, left.
And cook and the two footmen are complainin' again.
Kitson 先生, 我们的管家离开了。 厨师和两个杂役都在说这个
JAMIE: Haunted?
闹鬼？
MOLLIE: Mmm. But, I've never heard anything sir.
I sleep like a log and always have.
嗯。不过, 我从来没听到过什么, 先生。我睡觉跟一根木头似的, 总是这样
JAMIE: Aye. well, I'm glad you've got over the fright you had.
啊, 这样。我很高兴你已经克服了恐惧
JAMIE: Oh, yes, that horrible man.
Miss Ruth said it was all a game, but I dunno sir.
噢, 是的, 那个吓人的家伙。Ruth 小姐说只是个游戏, 不过我也搞不懂。
MOLLIE: I've never fainted before, sir. Truly I haven't.
我以前从来没有晕倒过, 先生。真的没有
JAMIE: Not "sir", "Jamie"!
不是“先生”, “Jamie”！
JAMIE: Tell me about Arthur Terrall.
告诉我一些 Arthur Terrall 的情况
MOLLIE: Miss Ruth's fiance, sir?
Ruth 小姐的未婚夫, 先生
JAMIE: Aye.
啊
MOLLIE: Oh, oh, he's a kind man, sir. Usually.
哦, 他是个好人, 先生。通常来说
JAMIE: Usually?
通常来说？
MOLLIE: Mmm. Well, when he's a bit odd or his temper's up,
as it has been lately,
嗯, 就是, 他有点怪, 或者脾气上来了, 就像最近那样
MOLLIE: I says to meself "Inkerman" and then it's all right.
我跟自己说, 估计“英克曼人”就是那样
JAMIE: "Inkerman"?
“英克曼人”？
MOLLIE: Yes sir. 'e was out in the Crimea, 'e was.
They do say Mr. Terrall was wounded out there.
是的先生, 他是从克里米亚来的, 他是。他们的确说过 Terrall 在那里受了伤
MOLLIE: Do you know, my uncle was killed at Inkerman, sir.
So, you see, I do know what it's like with soldiers.
你知道吗, 我叔叔就是在英克曼战死的, 先生。所以, 你看, 我还真知道士兵是怎样的
(备注：1854-1856年, 俄国与英、法为争夺小亚细亚地区权利而爆发“克里米亚战争“)
MOLLIE: Oh... oh, I'm sorry sir. I didn't mean to...
哦。。。哦, 对不起先生。我不是有意的。。。
MOLLIE: Well cook said to me that if I did some dusting it would be all right.
厨师跟我说, 我打扫打扫就可以了
MOLLIE: Oh, you won't tell the master, will you?
That I... Ah, ah... Thank you. Sorry sir.
哦, 你不会告诉主人的, 是吗？那我。。。啊。。谢谢你, 对不起,先生
DOCTOR: Sorry Mollie. Never mind, Mollie. That will do.
Yes, Mollie, thank you very much. It's all right, Mollie.
抱歉 Mollie, 不用在意, Moiilie, 这就行了, 好了, Mollie
DOCTOR: I wouldn't dream of telling him. Thank you very much, Bye-bye.
我不会告诉他的, 很谢谢你, 拜拜
DOCTOR: Hmm, you'll have to brush up on your history.
I can't be around to cover up for you all the time.
呜, 你得刷新一下你的历史知识了。我不可能总在你身边替你补课
(备注: Jamie 是172x年诞生的, 174x年开始跟随博士旅行, 所以他对后面的历史知道得不多)
DOCTOR: Now then, in the Crimean War, the English, the French
and the Turks fought the Russians...
这一次, 克里米亚战争, 英国人、法国人和土耳其人一起跟俄国人打
JAMIE: Oh, forget about all that!
哦, 忘了那些吧
DOCTOR: Oh, I thought you'd be interested. I watched
the Charge of the Light Brigade. Magnificent folly...
哦, 我以为你会感兴趣。我可见过轻骑兵发起的冲锋, 那可真是愚蠢。。。
(备注: 此处特指1854年10月克里米亚战争巴拉克拉瓦战役中,
英国轻骑兵向俄军发起的冲锋, 因命令传达错误而伤亡惨重。
因诗歌 The Charge of the Light Brigade 而受后人铭记)
DOCTOR: Look, where've you been?
我说, 你都去哪儿了？
DOCTOR: Oh, just looking around.
哦, 只是四处看看
JAMIE: Aye. What for? The TARDIS?!
啊, 看什么？TARDIS 吗？
DOCTOR: Jamie, you're in a temper!
Jamie, 你在闹脾气啊
JAMIE: Oh, am I? Is that bad then? Does that mean I won't
be co-operative - I won't do everything I'm told?
哦, 是吗？这很糟糕吧？是不是意味着我不会乖乖听话了？不会说什么我就做什么了？
DOCTOR: What was that?
这是什么话？
JAMIE: I overheard you and Waterfield!
我听到了你和 Waterfield 的对话！
DOCTOR: You were eavesdropping!
你居然在偷听！
JAMIE: Well, whatever it is, I don't like what you're doing.
不管怎样, 我不喜欢你现在做的事
DOCTOR: Now you listen to me...!
你听我说。。。！
JAMIE: No, Doctor, you're forgetting the TARDIS was stolen
and a man was murdered!
不, 博士, 你已经忘记 TARDIS 被偷了, 还有人被杀了
JAMIE:  Now, how am I supposed to tell when I see
you as friendly as you like with the murderer!
现在, 我看见你跟杀人凶手在一起跟朋友似的, 你让我怎么想呢？
DOCTOR: Waterfield did not murder that man!
Waterfield 没有杀那个人！
JAMIE: All right then, but he stole the TARDIS
and that still makes him a thief!
那好, 但他偷了 TARDIS, 他仍然还是一个小偷！
DOCTOR: The Daleks forced him to!
Daleks 强迫他干的
JAMIE: The Daleks! You keep telling me about the Daleks,
and I haven't even seen one!
Daleks！ 你一直跟我说 Daleks, 但我一个没见着。
JAMIE: You're always on about them, but where are they?!
你不停地说, 但他们在哪儿呢？
DOCTOR: Now you listen to me...!
你得听我说啊。。。！
JAMIE: No, you'll not get round me this time, Doctor.
不, 这次你别想忽悠我了, 博士
DOCTOR: You're up to something with Waterfield and Maxtible.
你跟 Waterfield 还有 Maxtible 在搞些什么
JAMIE: Now what is it? Some scientific invention?!
到底是什么呢? 某种科学发明吗？！
JAMIE: Ah, here's your friend.
啊, 你的朋友来了
DOCTOR: Just a little argument.
只是一点小争论
WATERFIELD: I heard voices raised.
我听着声音有点大了
JAMIE: That's not all you'll hear!
你听见的才不止这点呢
DOCTOR: Jamie seems to think that I'm lying to him.
Jamie 似乎认为我在欺骗他
JAMIE: Well, aren't you?!
怎么, 没有吗？
DOCTOR: He doesn't believe the Daleks are here.
他并不相信 Daleks 就在这里
WATERFIELD: It's the truth.
这是事实
JAMIE: Aye, the truth you told Arthur Terrall, maybe
- that your daughter was in Paris!
啊, 你还把事实告诉了 Arthur Terrall —— 你的女儿在巴黎！
WATERFIELD: I had to tell him that.
我只能那样跟他说
JAMIE: So, you've got another story to tell me?
所以, 你还有另外一个故事是给我的罗？
WATERFIELD: I tell you that the Daleks are holding my daughter
prisoner in the south wing of this house, Mr. McCrimmon.
我跟你说, Daleks 现在把我的女儿关押在了这栋房子的南面, McCrimmon 先生
JAMIE: Then why don't you try and get her back, eh?!
What are you doing?!
那你怎么不试着把她救回来, 嗯？你在忙些什么？
DOCTOR: : Well, what can I do? Now, be... be fair Jamie.
我能怎么做？现在。。。理智点 Jamie
DOCTOR: Waterfield's tied hand and foot because of his daughter
and we're tied hand and foot because of the TARDIS!
Waterfield 因为他女儿而投鼠忌器, 我们因为 TARDIS 而束手束脚
JAMIE: Aye, and that's all you can think about, isn't it?
The TARDIS?
啊, 你能想到的就只有这个, TARDIS, 是吗?
JAMIE: Well, you can all stand around doing nothing.
I'm sick to death of it!
你就站在那里什么也不做？我恶心死了！
DOCTOR: Now just where are you going?
你现在要去哪儿？
JAMIE: To be by myself for a bit. Do you mind?
一个人呆一会儿, 你管得着吗？
DOCTOR: No, not a bit. But, one word of warning.
Don't you try to be a one-man army. You leave well alone.
不, 管不着。但警告你一句话, 别想一个人逞英雄。你别管这事
DOCTOR: I won't have you ruining everything trying to rescue
Victoria Waterfield. Now, you understand?!
我不能允许你为了救 Victoria Waterfield 而毁了一切, 你听明白了没有？！
WATERFIELD: Well, are you sure you didn't go a little too far, Doctor?
唉, 你确定这样是不是有点过火了, 博士？
DOCTOR: Adding a little fuel to the fire.
Tell Maxtible that I'll be along to his laboratory shortly.
要火上浇点油。告诉 Maxtible 我很快就到他的实验室去
WATERFIELD: Oh, very well, Doctor. If you're sure.
哦, 好吧, 博士。如果你确定的话
DOCTOR: Oh yes, quite sure. Once our young friend has cooled
his heels a bit, he'll launch off on his own.
是的, 很确定。一旦我们的小朋友冷静一点, 他就会自己开始行动了
DOCTOR: And you dropped the hint about the south wing beautifully.
而且你也很漂亮地把南厢房的线索传递给他了
TERRALL: Well, what is it? You wanted to see me?
怎么, 什么事？你想要见我？
TOBY: Very good of you to talk to me, gov'nor.
你愿意跟我谈谈太好了, 先生
TERRALL: Well, never mind all that.
I'll give you two minutes, no more.
好了, 别提这个了。我之给你两分钟, 多了没有
TOBY: I want me rights. No more, no less.
我想要我的权利, 不多要, 也不能少给
TERRALL: What do you mean, "rights"?
你什么意思, “权利”？
TOBY: 'alf a guinea, you gave me, and it ain't what we said.
你刚才就给了半个基尼, 这不是我们之前说好的
TERRALL: You were lucky to get anything.
你还能拿到一点就不错了
TOBY: That ain't fair!
这不公平
TERRALL: You'll get no more from me. I warn you!
Keep away from this house, and this property.
你别想从我这里得到更多钱。我警告你, 离这个房子远点儿
TERRALL: Find the nearest road to London and take it!
找到去伦敦的路, 走吧
TOBY: Oh, yeah, London, sir. Yeah, I daresay
I could earn something for me stories there.
哦, 是啊, 伦敦, 先生。好啊, 我敢说, 到了那里我只凭讲故事就可以挣到钱啦
TERRALL: Stories?
故事？
TOBY: Oh, I won't detain an important gentleman like yourself.
Like as not me two minutes is up anyway.
哦, 我可不敢再耽误您这样的绅士了。不管喜欢不喜欢, 我的两分钟已经到了
TERRALL: What do you mean, "stories"?
你什么意思, “讲故事”？
TOBY: Ah, it's all right, sir. I'll take a stroll to London...
啊, 没事, 先生。我得上路去伦敦了。。。
TERRALL: Don't play with me!
别跟我玩花样！
TOBY: Get off me! If you must know, there's plenty
who'd pay to hear what I've got to tell 'em.
把手拿开！如果你非得知道, 有好多人愿意付钱听我给他们讲呢
TERRALL: Indeed?
真的？
TOBY: Yeah. You blows too hot and cold for me
- tellin' me this one minute and that the next, and not payin' up.
是啊, 你这一会儿阴一会儿晴, 一会儿这么说, 一会儿又那么说, 还不付钱
TERRALL: You know nothing.
你什么也不知道
TOBY: Don't I though?
我不知道吗, 哈？
TERRALL: Hmm. Who'd believe you anyway?
唔, 谁会信你呢？
TOBY: Pay me off, and there's the end of it!
把钱付了, 这事儿就算完了
TERRALL: Oh, blackmail is it?! Get out!
噢, 勒索是吗？ 滚出去！
(As Terrall lies unconscious, Toby goes through his pockets.)
(Terrall 躺在地上不省人事, Toby 趁机翻他的口袋)
(Toby finds some coins and a bunch of keys.)
(Toby 找了几个硬币和一串钥匙)
TOBY: Maybe I don't know much to tell, but I'll wager
I'll find something in the house that's worth me trouble.
也许我知道得不多, 但我打赌我能在这房子里找到点什么, 肯定有料
TOBY: So, I'll say thank ya, Mr. Terrall, sir!
那, 我就说声谢谢你了, Terrall 先生
(Mollie enters the sitting room carrying an old map.
(Mollie 进了客厅, 带着一份旧地图)
JAMIE: It's only me, Mollie!
是我, Mollie!
MOLLIE: It's over here, sir. I took it from the master's study.
就在这里, 先生。我从主人的书房里面拿出来的
JAMIE: It's marvellous. Thank you!
这太棒了, 谢谢你！
MOLLIE: 'ere, is this what you wanted?
这里, 这是你想要的吗？
(She hands Jamie a plan of the house.)
(她递给 Jamie 一份这栋房子的平面图)
JAMIE: Perfect, yes. Let's see, umm...
this is the south wing here?
非常好, 是的, 让我看一下, 嗯。。。这里是南厢房吗？
MOLLIE: Yes sir, but it's been closed off.
是的先生, 但这里被封了
JAMIE: Completely?
完全封了？
MOLLIE: Oh, no sir. Only 'cause of some repairs
about a twelve-month back. But the door may be locked.
哦, 不是, 先生。只是一些修缮工作, 都快一年了。不过门可能被锁住了
JAMIE: Can you show me?
你能指给我看一下吗？
MOLLIE: All right. What're you gonna do, sir?
行。你打算做什么, 先生？
(Jamie folds up the plan to take with him.)
(Jamie 折叠起地图, 带到身上)
JAMIE: Off to hunt a few wee ghosties, Mollie.
去抓几个小鬼, Mollie
DOCTOR: Every single one of Jamie's reactions
will be recorded on these Dalek machines?
Jamie 的每个动作都会在 Dalek 的这些机器上记录下来？
MAXTIBLE: And then transformed into thought patterns
on silver wire. A wonderful creation!
然后再转化成思维模型, 存储到银线。多么漂亮的发明！
DALEK: It is for you, Doctor, to select the major feelings
to make up this "human factor".
这是为你准备的, 博士, 你可以用它来挑选出那些组成“人类特质”的主要情感
DOCTOR: Oh, yes. I quite understand.
哦, 是的, 我完全明白
MAXTIBLE: We can rely on the Doctor to give us all cooperation.
我们可以信赖博士给予我们全面的合作
DALEK: We shall watch your every move.
我们会盯着你的一举一动
DOCTOR: I'm sure you will.
And every step of Jamie's progress will be covered?
我确信你们会这样的。Jamie 的每一步也会包含在内吧？
(Another Dalek enters.)
(又一个 Dalek 进来了)
DALEK: Yes.
是的
DALEK: The young human being is on his way.
这位年轻人已经在路上了
DOCTOR: Then the recording machines can be set in action.
那么录制设备就可以开启了
JAMIE: Here!
这里
MOLLIE: Yes, sir. I once remember the master stepping away from here.
是的, 先生。我记得有一次主人就从这里走过去的
MOLLIE: When he saw me, he was very cross and told me to keep away.
他看见我的时候非常生气, 让我离开
JAMIE: I see.
我明白了
(Jamie examines the back of the alcove.)
(Jamie 检查壁橱的后面)
(Toby has entered Maxtible's workroom, and is looking around.)
(Toby 已经进入了 Maxtible 的工作室, 正在四处摸索)
(A Daleks is watching him.)
(一个 Dalek 注视着他)
MOLLIE: What was that? What was that?!
那是什么？那是什么？
JAMIE: That was no ghost, Mollie, that's for sure.
That was a human voice!
那不是鬼, Mollie, 这是肯定的。那是一个人的声音！
MOLLIE: Oh, sir!
哦, 先生！
JAMIE: Look Mollie, take the candle and go back to your room.
Will you do that?
你看, Mollie, 拿着蜡烛, 回到你的房间去。你可以吗？
MOLLIE: Yes sir.
是的先生
JAMIE: Now, do you want me to see you safely there?
那, 你期望我陪你过去, 以确保你安全到达吗？
MOLLIE: No, no. I'll be all right.
不, 不用, 我没事的
(Jamie begins to examine the alcove area.)
(杰米开始检查壁橱区)
(He spots grease marks on the wall.)
(他发现墙上有油脂痕迹)
(Jamie presses the wall and the alove door opens.)
(杰米按了下墙壁, 壁橱门打开了)
(The metal spikes swing down across the entrance.)
(金属尖刺戳了下来, 挡住了入口)
(Jamie ducks underneath the spikes and through the alcove door.)
(杰米冒着腰, 躲着尖刺, 进了暗室的门)
(Jamie is walking slowly along a corridor.)
(Jamie 沿着走廊慢慢地走着)
Hello. Who are you?
JAMIE: 你好, 你是谁？